<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1 on Academic</title>
    <link>/publication_types/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 1 on Academic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Hugh Parsonage</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication_types/1/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A better super system: assessing the 2016 tax reforms</title>
      <link>/publication/assessing-the-2016-super-reforms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/assessing-the-2016-super-reforms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Winding back superannuation tax breaks is an acid test of our political system, and should be one of the first items of business in the current Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Federal Government’s plan to restrict superannuation tax breaks would create a fairer superannuation system more aligned to its purpose of providing income to supplement the Age Pension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan would not only trim overly generous super tax breaks enjoyed by the top 20 per cent of income earners – people wealthy enough to be comfortable in retirement and unlikely to qualify for the Age Pension – it would save about $800 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s proposals would affect about 4 per cent of superannuants, almost all with enough income and assets to prevent them from ever qualifying for a part Age Pension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claims that the proposed changes would be retrospective are incorrect. Many reforms affect investments made in the past, and no-one suggests they are retrospective. The changes will simply affect taxes paid on future super earnings, and entitlements to make future contributions to super.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternative proposals by the Australian Labor Party, which broadly supports the Coalition’s reforms, would save more than $2 billion a year. Many of these alternatives would further align superannuation with its core purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is broad agreement between the Government’s proposals and the ALP’s policy. If the Government concedes on some of the details to get a deal with the ALP in the Senate, it will probably improve the budget position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s considered position is built on principle, supported by the electorate, and our main parties largely agree on both ends and means. In these circumstances, a failure to get reform would signal there is little hope for either budget repair or wider economic reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the superannuation proposals are an important step in the right direction, they are only a step. Even with these reforms, super tax breaks will still overwhelmingly flow to high-income earners. And the long-term cost will remain unsustainable. Further changes will be needed in future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
