<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Academic</title>
    <link>/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Academic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Hugh Parsonage</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Age of entitlement: age-based tax breaks</title>
      <link>/publication/age-of-entitlement/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/age-of-entitlement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth Government could save about $\$1$ billion a year by winding back three tax breaks for older Australians that are unduly generous and have no sensible policy rationale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seniors pay less tax and get a higher rebate on private health insurance than do younger workers on the same income. They do so through the Seniors and Pensioners Tax Offset (SAPTO), a higher Medicare levy income threshold, and higher private health insurance rebates that are available only to older Australians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fewer people paying income tax – the rise of the “taxed-nots” – is in part due to age-based tax breaks. Despite their rising incomes and workforce participation rates, the proportion of over 65s paying tax has halved in the past 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the Commonwealth is running annual budget deficits of about $\$40$ billion and must make tough saving and spending decisions if it is not to hand an unsustainable bill to future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SAPTO and the Medicare levy income threshold should be wound back to save about $\$700$ million a year.
Reducing the private health insurance rebate so that seniors get the same rebate as younger Australians would save about $\$250$ million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only pensioners should qualify for SAPTO, while those with enough private income that they do not qualify for a full Age Pension should pay some income tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed changes would have little effect on the 40 per cent of seniors who receive a full Age Pension. They would most affect seniors who are wealthy enough to receive no pension or just a part pension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some argue that the tax breaks are a fair reward for paying tax while under 65. But in fact, large tax breaks for seniors are a relatively new invention not provided to previous generations. The current generation of seniors receives much more than its predecessors from government spending, particularly on health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Age-based tax breaks are badly designed to achieve valid policy purposes, such as increasing workforce participation or preserving adequate retirement incomes for poorer Australians. They might have been affordable when they were introduced over the past 20 years, but the country can no longer afford the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A better super system: assessing the 2016 tax reforms</title>
      <link>/publication/assessing-the-2016-super-reforms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/assessing-the-2016-super-reforms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Winding back superannuation tax breaks is an acid test of our political system, and should be one of the first items of business in the current Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Federal Government’s plan to restrict superannuation tax breaks would create a fairer superannuation system more aligned to its purpose of providing income to supplement the Age Pension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan would not only trim overly generous super tax breaks enjoyed by the top 20 per cent of income earners – people wealthy enough to be comfortable in retirement and unlikely to qualify for the Age Pension – it would save about $800 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s proposals would affect about 4 per cent of superannuants, almost all with enough income and assets to prevent them from ever qualifying for a part Age Pension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claims that the proposed changes would be retrospective are incorrect. Many reforms affect investments made in the past, and no-one suggests they are retrospective. The changes will simply affect taxes paid on future super earnings, and entitlements to make future contributions to super.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternative proposals by the Australian Labor Party, which broadly supports the Coalition’s reforms, would save more than $2 billion a year. Many of these alternatives would further align superannuation with its core purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is broad agreement between the Government’s proposals and the ALP’s policy. If the Government concedes on some of the details to get a deal with the ALP in the Senate, it will probably improve the budget position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government’s considered position is built on principle, supported by the electorate, and our main parties largely agree on both ends and means. In these circumstances, a failure to get reform would signal there is little hope for either budget repair or wider economic reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the superannuation proposals are an important step in the right direction, they are only a step. Even with these reforms, super tax breaks will still overwhelmingly flow to high-income earners. And the long-term cost will remain unsustainable. Further changes will be needed in future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
